Guide to the Eardley-Wilmot Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Eardley-Wilmot correspondence
1768-1817
OSB MSS 54
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.04
(3 boxes)
Correspondence between Eardley-Wilmot and his friends and colleagues. Included are letters from Spencer Perceval and Henry Ellis about the Lansdowne Manuscripts, which Eardley-Wilmot was trying to place at the British Museum; from Mark Noble about Eardley-Wilmot's book on Bishop Hough; and from William Franklin about a Silas Deane letter that Eardley-Wilmot sent to Franklin. There are also many letters about Eardley-Wilmot's book on his father; about political patronage in British parliament; and about political developments in Great Britain after the French Revolution.
Eardley-Wilmot, John, 1750-1815
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
JOHN EARDLEY-WILMOT (1750-1815)
John Eardley-Wilmot was the second son of Lord Chief Justice Sir John Eardley-Wilmot. Born in 1750, he graduated from University College, Oxford in 1769, was chosen fellow of All Souls' College, and was called to the Inner Temple bar in 1773. From 1781 to 1804 he held a Mastership in Chancery. He served in Parliament from 1776 to 1796, first as M.P. for Tiverton and later for Coventry.
A Whig, in 1783 he was appointed head of the Commission for Inquiring into the Losses, Services and Claims of the American Loyalists, reporting on claims for compensation filed by Loyalists after the conclusion of the Revolutionary War. Eardley-Wilmot published his "Historical View of the Commission....." in 1815. He organized the Freemasons' Hall Committee for the relief of French refugees in 1790.
In addition to his professional and political activities, Eardley-Wilmot was a book collector and antiquarian whose materials were essential to John Raynor's edition of Glanville's Tractatus de Legibus (1780), and who furthered the British Museum's purchase of the Lansdowne manuscript collection in 1807. He was also an early supporter of King's College in Halifax, Nova Scotia.
Other publications by Eardley-Wilmot include Memoirs of the Life of the Right Hon. Sir John Eardley Wilmot, Knt., with some original letters (1802, 1811) and The Life of the Reverend John Hough, D.D..... (1813).
Eardley-Wilmot died at Bruce Castle on June 26, 1815. His only son, John, was created Sir John Eardley Eardley-Wilmot in 1822, appointed lieutenant-governor of Van Dieman's Land (Tasmania) in 1843, and died in Hobart in 1847.
Scope and Contents
The John Eardley-Wilmot Correspondence consists of three boxes of letters to and copies of letters by John Eardley-Wilmot, as well as a small number of personal papers and related items. The papers span the dates 1769-1912; the bulk of the material dates from between 1793 and 1810.
The letters are alphabetically arranged by author; retained draft copies of letters by John Eardley-Wilmot himself are arranged alphabetically by recipient under the entry for Eardley-Wilmot.
The collection reflects the variety of Eardley-Wilmot's intellectual and charitable interests. Letters from Christopher Anstey, John Anstey, Sir Joseph Banks, Benjamin Incledon, and Mark Noble discuss Oliver Cromwell's correspondence; Wilmot's writings are the subject of letters from Wynley Blair, Charles Butler, Robert Cadell, Daniel Coke, James Ross and others. Wilmot's early letters to his lifelong friend Henry Michell are in Latin and Greek, drawing upon their literary studies at Cambridge.
Eardley-Wilmot's participation in the political patronage systems of his day can be traced in the letters of Thomas Blomefield, Isaac Crakell, Baron Harrowby, Bishop Hurd, John Phillips, and WIlliam Pitt. A 1779 letter to Nathaniel Ryder discusses Eardley-Wilmot's views on the American Revolution, while a later letter to Benjamin West comments on the compensation claims made to the Crown by American Loyalists.
Eardley-Wilmot was the executor of the estate of William Petty, 1st Marquis of Lansdowne, and his role in the purchase by the British Museum of Lansdowne's manuscripts is documented in letters by Sir Francis Baring; Sir Henry Ellis; William Petty-Fitzmaurice, 3rd marquis of Lansdowne; Joseph Planta, and Spencer Perceval. His abiding interest in King's College, Nova Scotia, is seen in letters from Shute Barrington, Charles Inglis, and John Inglis; while his activities on behalf of French refugees are noted in letters by the 1st marquis of Buckingham, Edmund Burke, Jean François de la Marche, Samuel Parr, John Hampden Trevor, and an unidentified contributor to his fund who signed himself "Philo-Caritos".
Other correspondents of note include William Franklin; John Bowles, who in an 1807 letter expressed fear that dancing and music "naturally lead to licentiousness and debauchery" in the poor; and Warren Dawson, who was likewise concerned with "mirth and jollity among the lower classes." The letters of Martha Wilmot, Edward Wilmot, and John Henry Michell are largely personal in nature.
Box 3, folder 157 contains a small number of personal papers of John Eardley-Wilmot, including his call to Temple Bar. Folders 158-160 contain bibliographical and biographical information.
Descriptions of individual letters or correspondences can be found in the notes appended to many of the folder entries in the finding aid.
Patronage, Political -- Great Britain; Deane, Silas, 1737-1789; Eardley-Wilmot, John, 1750-1815; Ellis, Henry, 1777-1869; Franklin, William, 1731-1813; Hough, John, 1651-1743; Noble, Mark, 1754-1827; Perceval, Spencer, 1762-1812
- Correspondence
  - "A"
    - "A" general, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Adams, James. ALS to John Eardley- Wilmot, [1802 or later] Jun (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ailesbury, Charles Brundenell-Bruce, 2d earl of, 1773-1856. 2 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1817 Jun, Sep (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ailesbury, Thomas Brundenell-Bruce, 1st earl of, 1729-1814. 1 letter to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1800 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Annesley, Francis. 2 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1807 Sep, 1808 Jul (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Scope and Contents
      Letters discuss the design and construction of Downing College, Cambridge.
    - Anstey, Christopher, 1724-1805. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, Bath, 1794 Jan (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Concerns the authenticity of a letter written by Oliver Cromwell.
    - Anstey, John, d. 1819. 2 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1802 Nov (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Discuss an Oliver Cromwell letter.
    - Aylesford, Heneage Finch, 4th earl of, 1751-1812. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1802 Dec (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Concerns the memoirs of Sir John Eardley-Wilmot.
  - "B"
    - "B" general, 1803-09 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Banks, Sir Joseph, 1743-1820. 2 ALS (signatures removed) to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1793 Dec, 1794 Jan (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Letters discuss an Oliver Cromwell letter.
    - Barentin, Charles Louis François de Paule de, 1738-1819. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1807 Jun (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Baring, Sir Francis, 1740-1810. 7 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1806 Apr-1807 Dec (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Letters discuss business matters especially relating to the sale of manuscripts and an estate (probably the Lansdowne estate).
    - Barrington, Shute, Bp. of Durham, 1734-1826. Letter to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1802 May (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Letter concerns patronage for Kings College Library, Nova Scotia.
    - Birch, Wynley. ALS to W. Digby, 1809 Apr (Box 1, Folder 14)
      On the life of John Hough, Bp. of Worcester.
    - Blakiston, Anne. 5 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1806 Dec-1807 Apr (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Letters deal with an attempt to have Eardley-Wilmot secure a public position for Charles Blakiston, age 18, and failing this the letters deal with finding any means of respectable employment.
    - Blomefield, Thomas, 1744-1822. 2 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1806 Feb, 1807 Sep (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Discusses the expedition against Copenhagen. Blomefield commanded the artillery.
    - Bowles, John. ALS to John Eardley- Wilmot, 1807 Sep (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Letter concerns a fair and attempts to have it strictly regulated. Bowles is afraid that dancing and music are not harmless amusements for the lower classes, because of lack of education and different habits, "pleasures which are harmless and safe in one case, naturally lead to licentiousness and debauchery in the other."
    - Browne, J. M. 2 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1794 Jan (Box 1, Folder 18)
      About foreign and domestic problems in government.
    - Buckingham, George Nugent-Temple- Grenville, 1st marquis of, 1753-1813. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1806 Jun (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Letter concerns Eardley-Wilmot's resignation as Commissioner for the French Emigrants and, as a reward, a position for one of his sons as "one of the Commissioners of Appeal in Excise Causes."
    - Burke, Edmund, 1729-1797. 2 ALS (signatures removed) to John Eardley- Wilmot, 1792 Oct, 1793 Nov (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Letters deal with Wilmot's work with French refugees.
    - Butler, Charles, 1750-1832. ALS and 1 letter to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1795 Jan, 1799 Sep (Box 1, Folder 21)
      On the memoirs of Sir John Eardley- Wilmot.
    - Butler, George, 1774-1853. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1805 Jun (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "C"
    - "C" general, 1793-1809 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Cadell, Robert, 1788-1849. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Concerns the publication of the memoirs of Sir John Eardley-Wilmot.
    - Carrington, Robert Smith, 1st baron, 1752-1838. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1807 Aug (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Personal matters.
    - Carron de la Carrière, Abbé Guy Toussaint Julien, 1760-1821. 2 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1803 Nov, 1807 Jun (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Letters discuss personal matters.
    - Coke, Daniel Parker, 1745-1825. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1802 Nov (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Cornwallis, Charles Cornwallis, 1st marquis, 1738-1805. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1787 Jul (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Concerns a patronage position.
    - Cowper, Henry, [1758-1840]? ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1803 Dec (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Thanks Wilmot for a present.
    - Crakell, Isaac. 7 ALS to John Eardley- Wilmot, 1809 Mar-1810 Oct (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Letters deal with a successful attempt by Crakell to obtain a patronage position for which Eardley-Wilmot's influence was necessary.
  - "D"
    - "D" general, 1802-07 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Dalrymple, Sir Hew Whitefoord, 1750-1830. 3 ALS to John Eardley- Wilmot, 1770 Jul-1785 May (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Dartmouth, George Legge, 3d earl of, 1755-1810. Letter to John Eardley- Wilmot, 1802 Nov (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Letter thanks Wilmot for the present of a book.
    - Dartmouth, William Legge, 2d earl, 1731-1801. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1792 Feb (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Letter of sympathy on the death of Sir John Eardley-Wilmot.
    - Digby, William. 6 ALS to John Eardley- Wilmot, 1809 Apr-Aug (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Letters deal with Bishop John Hough.
    - Disney, John, 1746-1816. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1809 Apr (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "E"
    - "E" general, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Eardley-Wilmot, John, 1750-1815
      - ALS (copy) to George Nugent-Temple- Grenville, 1st marquis of Buckingham, 1806 Jun (Box 2, Folder 38)
        Letter expresses appreciation for the offer made to Wilmot's son concerning a position as Commissioner of Appeal in Excise Courses, and also asks that Wilmot be relieved, for reasons of health, from the Commission for the French Emigrants.
      - ALS (copy) to Edmund Burke, 1795 Feb (Box 2, Folder 39)
        Letter is reply to Burke's letter to Wilmot of 1795 Feb 6. Letter discusses the morale of the country. "[T]he People in general do not seem apprized of the real state of the Country, namely that the Enemy is at the Gate."
      - ALS to Eardley-Wilmot, Sir John Eardley, 1808 May 6 (Box 2, Folder 40)
        Concerning travel, meetings, and his son.
      - AL (copy) to John Scott, 1st earl of Eldon, 1807 Oct (Box 2, Folder 41)
        Congratulates Scott for resuming the great seal and presents him with a collection of John Hewlitt's sermons.
      - ALS (copy) to Charles Long, Baron Farnborough, 1793 Mar (Box 2, Folder 42)
        Deals with the affairs of Mr. Marsh.
      - ALS (copy) to William Gilpin, 1810 May (Box 2, Folder 43)
        Wilmot declines for reasons of time and health an invitation to help publish and write either a biography of William Gilpin or a collection of his correspondence. Indicates how he would organize such an undertaking.
      - ALS (copy) to Nathaniel Ryder, 1st baron of Harrowby, 1779 Nov (Box 2, Folder 44)
        Letter expresses Wilmot's position on the Revolutionary War. At one point in the letter Wilmot refers to the "Americans" but this mistake is corrected by strikeovers and the insertion of the word "Colonies."
      - ALS (copy) to Francis Rawdon- Hastings, 1st marquis of Hastings, 1787 Jun (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - AL (copy) to Henry Petty- Fitzmaurice, 3d marquess of Lansdowne, 1806 Mar (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - ALS (copy) to Charles Manners-Sutton, 1812 Sep (Box 2, Folder 47)
        Letter recommends that John Inglis be chosen to replace his father Charles Inglis as Bishop of Nova Scotia.
      - 15 ALS to Henry Michell, 1769-70, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48-49)
        14 ALS in Latin and 1 in Greek to Michell, an accomplished Classical scholar, containing various quotations, epigrams, and discussions of Latin authors, as well as personal news.
      - ALS (copy) to Brownlow North, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 50)
        Tries to convince the Bishop to change the residence of Rev. Rivett, a "near Relation" to Wilmot.
      - ALS (copy) to Spencer Perceval, 1807 Apr (Box 2, Folder 51)
        Letter deals with the Lansdowne Manuscript Collection and Wilmot's suggestion that it be sold to the government and deposited in the British Museum.
      - 3 ALS (copies) to William Pitt, 1792 Nov-1795 Feb (Box 2, Folder 52)
        Asks to be replaced as Master in Chancery and to be appointed Welch Judge; warns him of restlessness among lower classes. Asks for pension for Mr. Marsh. Discusses war in Europe and warns of invasion in England; worried about lack of unity in England, especially regarding the "disaffected within the Kingdom."
      - ALS (copy) to John Freeman-Mitford, 1st baron of Redesdale, 1805 Jun (Box 2, Folder 53)
        Seeks a different appointment for a relative of Wilmot's.
      - ALS (copy) to Mr. Rose, 1793 Jun (Box 2, Folder 54)
        Letter discusses the affairs of a certain Mr. Marsh.
      - ALS to Mrs. Statham, 1809 Nov 18 (Box 2, Folder 55)
        Concerning personal relations and business matters.
      - ALS (copy) to Brook Watson, 1803 Mar (Box 2, Folder 56)
        Letter deals with an attempt by Wilmot to obtain funds for the college in Windsor, Nova Scotia. Wilmot knows of a trust whose funds were to be used to establish a (Royal) College in New England.
      - ALS (copy) to Benjamin West, 1809 Jun (Box 2, Folder 57)
        Letter gives an accounting of the claims of American Loyalists upon England for damages incurred during the American Revolution.
      - AL (copy?) and poem to Robert R. Wilmot (cousin), 1813 Nov 13 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      - 4 ALS to Matt Wren, 1769 Oct-1770 Jan (Box 2, Folder 59)
        Letters discuss Wilmot's election as fellow of All Souls College. The last two letters describe Wilmot's life in London and relate some of Parliament's actions.
      - ALS to unnamed recipient, 1797 Aug (Box 2, Folder 60)
        Letter contains Wilmot's suggestions for a proper education leading to a study of law.
      - ALS to unnamed recipient, 1807 Jan 1 (Box 2, Folder 61)
        Concerning personal matters and business relations.
      - ALS to unnamed recipient(s), 1807 Apr (Box 2, Folder 62)
        Concerning the catalogue of the Marquis of Lansdowne's manuscripts and the proposal to apply to Parliament for funds for their purchase by the British Museum.
      - ALS to unnamed recipient, 1807 Nov 26 (Box 2, Folder 63)
        Concerning the delivery of the Lansdowne manuscripts to the British Museum and Eardley-Wilmot's signature of the catalogue.
    - Eardley-Wilmot, Sir John Eardley, 1783-1847. 2 ALS to John Eardley- Wilmot, 1810 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 64)
      Letters discuss both personal and public matters (Duke of Wellington's campaign).
    - Ellis, Sir Henry, 1777-1869. ALS to Joseph Planta, 1807 Sep (Box 2, Folder 65)
      Concerns a collection of manuscripts.
    - Erksine, Thomas Erksine, 1st baron, 1750-1823. ALS (signature cut) to John Eardley-Wilmot, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - "F"
    - "F" general, 1802-06 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Fisher, A. ALS to William Digby, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 68)
      Letter concerns information about Bishop Hough.
    - Fox, Charles James, 1749-1806. ALS (signature cut) to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1783 Oct 8 (Box 2, Folder 69)
      Letter informs Wilmot of a coming session of Parliament and warns Wilmot that "Business of the greatest Importance is intended to come on immediately."
    - Franklin, William, 1731-1813. ALS and 1 letter to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1801 May, 1806 Oct (Box 2, Folder 70)
      Letter of 1806 deals with Silas Deane's advocacy of a reconciliation with England during the Revolution. Franklin dislikes the "violent Hot heads in Congress." Refers to Deane's secretary in Paris, presumably Edward Bancroft, a British double agent.
  - "G"
    - "G" general, 1802-09 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Gaskin, George, 1751-1829. 1 printed letter, signed, to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1806 Dec (Box 2, Folder 72)
      Letter informs Wilmot that he has been chosen to be a subscribing member in the Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge and will be a member as soon as he pays "a voluntary sum."
    - Gilpin, William, 1724-1804. 15 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1793 Dec-1801 Jul (Box 2, Folder 73)
      Letters discuss family matters and on occasion deal with matters of state. One letter (1800 Oct 29) talks about Gilpin's son (John Bernard?) and his fortunes in America.
    - Grantham, Thomas Philip de Grey, 3d baron, 1781-1859. ALS to John Eardley- Wilmot, [After 1804] Feb (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Gregory, George, 1754-1808. 4 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1805 Feb (Box 2, Folder 75)
      Letters deal with personal matters including the memoirs of Sir John Eardley-Wilmot. One letter (1805 Feb) deals with Gregory's son and his plans to obtain legal training; same letter describes the living of West Ham, Essex, to which Gregory was presented in 1803.
    - Gregory, John. ALS to John Eardley- Wilmot, 1808 Mar (Box 2, Folder 76)
      Letter informs Wilmot of the death of George Gregory.
  - "H"
    - "H" general, 1803-09 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Hardwicke, Philip Yorke, 3d earl of, 1757-1834. ALS and 1 letter to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1796 Jul, 1806 Dec (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Hargrave, Francis, 1741?-1821. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1783 Jan (Box 2, Folder 79)
      Letter concerns two books which were given to Hargrave by Wilmot.
    - Harrowby, Nathaniel Ryder, 1st baron, 1735-1803. 5 ALS to John Eardley- Wilmot, 1777 Nov-1802 Nov (Box 2, Folder 80)
      Letters deal with general parliamentary matters. 1777 Nov 29 contains the confession that Harrowby cannot support an unnamed proposal because it "would effectually disappoint every future Prospect of a Parliamentary Establishment for my Son."
    - Hastings, Francis Rawdon-Hastings, 1st marquis of, 1754-1826. 5 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1787 Jun-1804 Nov (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Heath, James, 1757-1834. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1809 Dec (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Hewlett, John, 1762-1844. 2 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1803 May, 1808 Nov (Box 2, Folder 83)
      First letter thanks Wilmot for his contributions towards securing a home for Hewlett; the second sharply criticizes "those fanatics who are called Methodists."
    - Hurd, Richard, Bp. of Worcester, 1720-1808. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1790 Aug (Box 2, Folder 84)
      Letter deals with an attempt to have the Bishop give a patronage position to one of Wilmot's friends.
  - "I"
    - "I" general, 1802 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Incledon, Benjamin, 1730-1796. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1794 Jan (Box 2, Folder 86)
      Letter concerns an Oliver Cromwell letter.
    - Inglis, Charles, Bp. of Nova Scotia, 1734-1816. 5 ALS to John Eardley- Wilmot, 1802 Oct-1805 Dec (Box 2, Folder 87)
      Letters concern the King's College at Windsor, Nova Scotia, the need for it, its history and progress; his son was the first student. Letters discuss current events and people. Sends a copy of his protest, included.
    - Inglis, John, Bp. of Nova Scotia, 1777-1850. 21 ALS to John Eardley- Wilmot, 1802 Apr-1810 Nov (Box 2, Folder 88)
      Letters primarily deal with King's College of Nova Scotia, including administrative problems. Politics are also discussed and the threat of Bonaparte increases in the later letters. 1804 July 25 speaks of sectionalism in America. 1807 Nov 13 talks about the possibility of war between the U. S. and England. 1808 May 29 deals with American politics.
  - "J"
    - "J" general, 1803 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - "K"
    - "K" general, 1802 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - "L"
    - "L" general, 1802-06 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - La Marche, Jean-François de, Bp. of St. Pol de Léon, 1729-1806. 6 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1793 Apr-1806 Apr (Box 2, Folder 92)
      Letters deal with the conditions of French refugees.
    - Lansdowne, Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, 3d marquess of, 1780-1863. 5 ALS and 1 letter to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1805 May-1808 May (Box 2, Folder 93)
      Letters deal with Wilmot's selection as Executor for Lansdowne's father's estate.
    - Lansdowne, William Petty, 1st marquis of, 1737-1805. 12 ALS to John Eardley- Wilmot, 1791 Aug-1804 Jan (Box 2, Folder 94)
      Letters deal mostly with personal matters. A few concern politics, such as the issue of French refugees (1792 Sep 23), where Petty shows his dislike of Edmund Burke.
    - Lifford, Alicia (Oliver) Hewitt, viscountess, d. 1845. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1804 Nov (Box 2, Folder 95)
      Letter discusses personal matters.
    - Lifford, James Hewitt, 1st viscount, 1709-1789. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1787 Nov (Box 2, Folder 96)
      Discusses family matters.
  - "M"
    - "M" general, 1793-1806 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Mackie, John, 1748-1831. 2 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1810 Mar-Jul (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Mansfield, Sir James, 1733-1821. ALS and 1 letter to John Eardley-Wilmot (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Michell, I. C. 5 ALS to John Eardley- Wilmot, 1809 Jun-Nov (Box 2, Folder 100)
      Letters concern Wilmot's desire for information about John Hough, Bp. of Worcester.
    - Michell, John Henry. 35 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1792 Feb-1809 Dec (Box 2, Folder 101)
      Letters discuss personal matters. Michell often would flatter Wilmot as best he could. In particular, 1792 Sep 20 describes Wilmot as aiding French refugees and blames the French Revolution on the "impiety of Voltaire." Pays tribute to the Bp. of Leon in 1807 Jun 16.
  - "N"
    - "N" general, 1794-1809 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Nash, Treadway Russell, 1725-1811. 2 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Noble, Mark, 1754-1827. 2 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1793 Dec,1809 May (Box 2, Folder 104)
      Letters concern Wilmot's study of Bishop Hough and Noble's study of Oliver Cromwell.
    - North, Brownlow, Bp. of Winchester, 1741-1820. ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1799 Mar (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - "O"
    - "O" general, [n.y.] Jan 5 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - "P"
    - "P" general, 1794-1810 (Box 3, Folder 107)
    - Parr, Samuel, 1747-1825. 2 ALS to John Eardley-Wilmot, 1793 Jun (Box 3, Folder 108)